<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Model Selection on Datumorphism</title><link>/wiki/model-selection/</link><description>Recent content in Model Selection on Datumorphism</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/wiki/model-selection/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Model Selection</title><link>/wiki/model-selection/model-selection/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/wiki/model-selection/model-selection/</guid><description>Suppose we have a generating process that generates some numbers based on a distribution. Based on a data sample, we could reconstruct some sort of theoretical models to represent the actual generating process.
Which is a Good Model? (1)The black curve represent the generating process. The red rectangle is a very simple model that captures some major samples. The blue step-wise model is capturing more sample data but with more parameters.</description></item><item><title>Goodness-of-fit</title><link>/wiki/model-selection/goodness-of-fit/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/wiki/model-selection/goodness-of-fit/</guid><description>Does the data agree with the model?
Calculate the distance between data and model predictions. Apply Bayesian methods such as likelihood estimation: likelihood of observing the data if we assume the model; the results will be a set of fitting parameters. &amp;hellip; Why don&amp;rsquo;t we always use goodness-of-fit as a measure of the goodness of a model?
We may experience overfitting. The model may not be intuitive. This is why we would like to balance it with parsimony using some measures of generalizability.</description></item><item><title>Measures of Generalizability</title><link>/wiki/model-selection/measures-of-generalizability/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/wiki/model-selection/measures-of-generalizability/</guid><description>To measure the generalization, we define a generalization error,
$$ \begin{align} \mathcal G = \mathcal L_{P}(\hat f) - \mathcal L_E(\hat f), \end{align} $$ where $\mathcal L_{P}$ is the population loss, $\mathcal L_E$ is the empirical loss, and $\hat f$ is our model by minimizing the empirical loss.
However, we do not know the actual joint probability $p(x, y)$ of our dataset $\{x_i, y_i\}$. Thus the population loss is not known. In machine learning, we usually use cross validation where we split our dataset into train and test dataset.</description></item><item><title>Parsimony of Models</title><link>/wiki/model-selection/parsimony-of-models/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/wiki/model-selection/parsimony-of-models/</guid><description>For models with a lot of parameters, the goodness-of-fit is very likely to be very high. However, it is also likely to generalize bad. So we need measure of generalizability
Here parsinomy gives us a few advantages.
easy to perceive better generalizations</description></item></channel></rss>