<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>cards/statistics/fia.md on Datumorphism</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/links/cards/statistics/fia.md/</link><description>Recent content in cards/statistics/fia.md on Datumorphism</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://datumorphism.leima.is/links/cards/statistics/fia.md/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Model Selection</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/model-selection/model-selection/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/model-selection/model-selection/</guid><description>Suppose we have a generating process that generates some numbers based on a distribution. Based on a data sample, we could reconstruct some sort of theoretical models to represent the actual generating process.
Which is a Good Model? (1)The black curve represent the generating process. The red rectangle is a very simple model that captures some major samples. The blue step-wise model is capturing more sample data but with more parameters.
In the above example, the red model on the left is not that good in most cases while the blue model seems to be better. In reality, the choice depends on the usage of the model.</description></item><item><title>Minimum Description Length</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/cards/statistics/mdl/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/cards/statistics/mdl/</guid><description>The minimum description length, aka, MDL, is based on the relations between regularity and data compression. (See Kolmogorov complexity Kolmogorov Complexity Description of Data The measurement of complexity is based on the observation that the compressibility of data doesn&amp;rsquo;t depend on the &amp;ldquo;language&amp;rdquo; used to describe the compression process that much. This makes it possible for us to find a universal language, such as a universal computer language, to quantify the compressibility of the data. One intuitive idea is to use a programming language to describe the data. If we have a sequence of data, … for more about data descriptions.</description></item></channel></rss>