<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Statistical Estimation on Datumorphism</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/categories/statistical-estimation/</link><description>Recent content in Statistical Estimation on Datumorphism</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://datumorphism.leima.is/categories/statistical-estimation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why Estimation Theory</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/statistical-estimation/why-estimation-theory/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/statistical-estimation/why-estimation-theory/</guid><description>In statistics, we work with samples. For example, the sample mean is easily calculated. However, it is the population mean that is more valuable.
Suppose we have one sample $S_i$, which is used to calculate the mean of the sample $\mu_i$. We have two key problems to solve at this moment.
Can we use this sample mean $\mu_i$ to represent the population mean $\mu_p$? How good is our estimations? To answer these questions, we need to work out the properties of the samples themselves and work out a theory to instruct us to infer population statistics from sample statistics.</description></item><item><title>Confidence Interval</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/statistical-estimation/confidence-interval/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/statistical-estimation/confidence-interval/</guid><description>We will use upper cases for the abstract variable and lower cases for the actual numbers.
Why is Confidence Interval Needed? Suppose I sample the population multiple times, the mean value $\mu_i$ of the sample is calculated for each sample. It is a good question to ask how different these $\mu_i$ are compared to the true mean $\mu_p$ of the population.
In this article, we would need to specify several notations.
$X$ is the quantity we are measuring. $\bar X$ is the mean of the quantity $X$. Confidence Interval This theorem states that the probability for the true mean $\mu_p$ to fall into a specific range can be calculated using</description></item><item><title>Conformal Prediction</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/statistical-estimation/conformal-prediction/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/statistical-estimation/conformal-prediction/</guid><description>Conformal prediction is a method to predict a consistent confidence interval in an on-line setting.
on-line
An on-line setting is to predict continuously for sequentially incoming data points. For example, we predict $x_n$ for given data points $\{\!\{x_1, \cdots, x_{n-1}\}\!\}$. Then we predict $x_{n+1}$ using $\{\!\{x_1, \cdots, x_{n}\}\!\}$. Nonconformity Measure For a new incoming data point $x$, and an existing [[multiset]] Multiset, mset or bag A bag is a set in which duplicate elements are allowed. An ordered bag is a list that we use in programming. of data points
$$ B_n = \{\!\{x_1, \cdots, x_{n}\}\!</description></item></channel></rss>