<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>feature engineering on Datumorphism</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/tags/feature-engineering/</link><description>Recent content in feature engineering on Datumorphism</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://datumorphism.leima.is/tags/feature-engineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Feature Engineering</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/feature-engineering/overview/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/feature-engineering/overview/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Data Types and Level of Measurement in Machine Learning</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/feature-engineering/data-types/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/feature-engineering/data-types/</guid><description>Types of Data There are several debatable categorization methods of data.
The first widely spread theory, or level of measurement, is by S. Stevens. The theory categorizes data into four types, nominal, ordinal, interval, and ratio.
Other methods are proposed for other fields of research. For example, N. R. Chrisman proposed a different method for cartography. However, these are not generic enough for data science. They are more general than a specific field of research.
For machine learning, many statistical data types have been proposed. Some examples of data types and their relations with the level of measurement are shown in the following chart.</description></item><item><title>Deal with Rare Categories Using Pandas</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/til/data/deal-with-rare-categories-using-pandas/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/til/data/deal-with-rare-categories-using-pandas/</guid><description>We will illustrate how to deal with rare categories using pandas mask.
import pandas as pd ############# # Create fake names frequent_names = list(&amp;#39;ABC&amp;#39;) rare_names = list(&amp;#39;DEF&amp;#39;) dataset = sum( [[i]*10 for i in frequent_names] + [[i]*2 for i in rare_names], [] ) # Create a series based on the names series = pd.Series(dataset) print(series) # Find the counts of the names in the series series_counts = series.value_counts() print(series_counts) # Find names that has less than 10 counts # And create a mask mask = series.isin(series_counts.loc[series_counts&amp;lt;10].index) print(mask) # Set these rare names to X series[mask] = &amp;#39;X&amp;#39; # Check the new series print(series.</description></item><item><title>Dealing with Missing Data in Machine Learning</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/feature-engineering/missing-data/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/feature-engineering/missing-data/</guid><description>How to Deal with Missing Data Remove Listwise deletion: Remove the whole record; Works if the missing values are random. Removing values causes problem in many aspects. For example, we can not just delete data when applying our models. Replace with most frequent value central tendency: median, mean, etc fixed value: a string etc New Category: define a new category for missing data Convert the column to a binary valued column indicating if the feature is missing or not. Tools pandas sklearn: Imputer @ResidentMario/missingno : visualize missing data</description></item></channel></rss>