<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>wiki/machine-learning/tree-based/decision-tree.md on Datumorphism</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/links/wiki/machine-learning/tree-based/decision-tree.md/</link><description>Recent content in wiki/machine-learning/tree-based/decision-tree.md on Datumorphism</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://datumorphism.leima.is/links/wiki/machine-learning/tree-based/decision-tree.md/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Random Forest</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/tree-based/random-forest/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/tree-based/random-forest/</guid><description>Random forest is an ensemble method based on decision trees. Instead of using one decision tree and model on all the features, the decision tree method can model on a random set of features (feature subspace) using many decision trees and make decisions by democratizing the trees.
Given a proper dataset $\mathscr D(\mathbf X, \mathbf y)$, the ensemble of trees is denoted as ${f_i(\mathbf X)}$, will predict an ensemble of results. There are several key ideas in random forests.
Are the predicted results representative? How to democratize the ensemble of results? What determines the quality of the predictions? Margin, Strength, and Correlations The margin of the model, the strength of the trees, and the correlation between the trees are crucial to answer the questions.</description></item><item><title>Gini Impurity</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/cards/machine-learning/measurement/gini-impurity/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/cards/machine-learning/measurement/gini-impurity/</guid><description>The code used in this article can be found in this repo. Suppose we have a dataset $\{0,1\}^{10}$, which has 10 records and 2 possible classes of objects $\{0,1\}$ in each record.
The first example we investigate is a pure 0 dataset.
object 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 For such an all-0 dataset, we would like to define its impurity as 0.</description></item><item><title>Information Gain</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/cards/machine-learning/measurement/information-gain/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/cards/machine-learning/measurement/information-gain/</guid><description>Information gain is a frequently used metric in calculating the gain during a split in tree-based methods.
First o all, the entropy of a dataset if defined as
$$ S = - sum_i p_i \log p_i - sum_i (1-p_i)\log p_i, $$
where $p_i$ is the probability of a class.
The information gain is the difference between the entropy.
For example, in a decision tree algorithm, we would split a node. Before splitting, we assign a label $m$ to the node,
$$ S_m = - p_m \log p_m - (1-p_m)\log p_m. $$
After the splitting, we have two groups that contributes to the entropy, group $L$ and group $R$,</description></item></channel></rss>