<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Energy-based Model on Datumorphism</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/categories/energy-based-model/</link><description>Recent content in Energy-based Model on Datumorphism</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://datumorphism.leima.is/categories/energy-based-model/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>MaxEnt Model</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/energy-based-model/maxent-energy-based-model/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/energy-based-model/maxent-energy-based-model/</guid><description>The Maximum Entropy model, aka MaxEnt model, is a fascinating generative model as it is based on a very intuitive idea from statistical physics - the Principle of Maximum Entropy.
The Idea The essence of the MaxEnt model is that the underlying probability distribution $p(x)$ of the random variables $x$ should
gives the whole system the largest uncertainty, while producing reasonable observables. Uncertainty The uncertainty of the whole system is described by the Shannon entropy based on the probability distributions $p(x)$,
$$ S[p] = -\operatorname{Tr} p(x) \log p(x). $$
The [[Shannon entropy]] Coding Theory Concepts The code function produces code words.</description></item><item><title>Boltzmann Machine</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/energy-based-model/boltzmann-machine/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/energy-based-model/boltzmann-machine/</guid><description>Boltzmann machine is much like a spin glass model in physics. In short words, Boltzmann machine is a machine that has nodes that can take values, and the nodes are connected through some weight. It is just like any other neural nets but with complications and theoretical implications.
Boltzmann machine is usually used as a generative model.
Boltzmann Machine and Physics To obtain a good understanding of Boltzmann machine for a physicist, we begin with Ising model. We construct a system of neurons ${ s_i}$ which can take values of 1 or -1, where each pair of them $s_i$ and $s_j$ is connected by weight $J_{ij}$.</description></item><item><title>Restricted Boltzmann Machine</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/energy-based-model/restricted-boltzmann-machine/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/energy-based-model/restricted-boltzmann-machine/</guid><description>Latent variables introduce extra correlations between the nodes in a network. Introducing hidden units can also help us remove the direct connection between some nodes in a Boltzmann machine and create a restricted Boltzmann machine. A restricted Boltzmann machine requires less computation while having some expressing power.
Given Ising like interactions between the nodes, flipping node V1 is likely to also flip node V2 as they are connected through hidden unit H1. They are correlated. Removing the hidden unit leaves us two uncorrelated units.
The Ising Model Given a Ising-like energy function (c.f. [[MaxEnt Model]] MaxEnt Model Maximum Entropy models makes least assumption about the data )</description></item><item><title>Diffusion Models for Forecasting</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/energy-based-model/diffusion-model/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/energy-based-model/diffusion-model/</guid><description>Objective In a denoising diffusion model, given
an input $\mathbf x^0$ drawn from a complicated and unknown distribution $q(\mathbf x^0)$, we find
a latent space with a simple and manageable distribution, e.g., normal distribution, and the transformations from $\mathbf x^0$ to $\mathbf x^n$, as well as the transformations from $\mathbf x^n$ to $\mathbf x^0$. An Example For example, with $N=5$, the forward process is
flowchart LR x0 -- x1 -- x2 -- x3 -- x4 -- x5 and the reverse process is
flowchart LR x5 -- x4 -- x3 -- x2 -- x1 -- x0 The joint distribution we are searching for is</description></item></channel></rss>