<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Unsupervised Learning on Datumorphism</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/tags/unsupervised-learning/</link><description>Recent content in Unsupervised Learning on Datumorphism</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://datumorphism.leima.is/tags/unsupervised-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Unsupervised Learning</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/unsupervised/overview/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/unsupervised/overview/</guid><description>Unsupervised Learning!
Principle components analysis Clustering K-means Clustering Algorithm:
Assign data points to a group Iterate through until no change: Find centroid Find the point that is closest to the centroids. Assign that data point to the corresponding group of the centroids. How Many Groups
The art of chosing K. Hierarchical Clustering Bottom-up hierarchical groups can be read out from the dendrogram.</description></item><item><title>Unsupervised Learning: PCA</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/unsupervised/pca/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/unsupervised/pca/</guid><description>We use the Einstein summation notation in this article. Principal Component Analysis (PCA) is a commonly used trick for dimensionality reduction so that the new features represents most of the variances of the data.
Representations of Dataset In theory, a dataset can be represented by a matrix if we specify the basis. However, the initial given basis is not always the most convinient one. Suppose we find a new set of basis for the dataset, the matrix representation may be simpler and easier to use.
For convenience, we do not distinguish the representation and the abstract dataset in this article.</description></item><item><title>Logistic Regression</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/linear/logistic-regression/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/linear/logistic-regression/</guid><description>In a classification problem, given a list of features values $x$ and their corresponding classes $\{c_i\}$, the posterior for of the classes, aka conditional probability of the classes, is
$$ p(C=c_i\mid X=x). $$
Likelihood
The likelihood of the data is
$$ p(X=x\mid C=c_i). $$
Logistic Regression for Two Classes For two classes, the simplest model for the posterior is a linear model,
$$ \log \frac{p(C=c_1\mid X=x) }{p(C=c_2\mid X=x)} = \beta_0 + \beta_1 \cdot x, $$
which is equivalent to
$$ p(C=c_1\mid X=x) = \exp\left(\beta_0 + \beta_1 \cdot x\right) p(C=c_2\mid X=x) . $$
Why
The reason that we proposing a linear model for the quantity</description></item><item><title>Unsupervised Learning: SVM</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/unsupervised/svm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/unsupervised/svm/</guid><description>SVM is calculating a hyperplane to separate the data points into groups according to the label.
Hyperplane A hyperplane is defined to be of the following form
$$ \begin{equation} \boldsymbol{\beta} \cdot \mathbf x = \beta_0. \end{equation} $$
where $\boldsymbol\beta$ is the normal vector to the plane and is required to be constant.
It is straight forward to show that the distance $d$ from an arbitrary point $\mathbf x'$ to the hyperplane is
$$ \begin{equation} d = \boldsymbol\beta \cdot \mathbf x' - \beta_0. \end{equation} $$
A Few Key Concepts in SVM Though the concept of SVM is simple, one might find the algorithm to be quite complicated at first glance.</description></item></channel></rss>