<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>wiki/statistics/correlation-analysis-chi-square.md on Datumorphism</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/links/wiki/statistics/correlation-analysis-chi-square.md/</link><description>Recent content in wiki/statistics/correlation-analysis-chi-square.md on Datumorphism</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://datumorphism.leima.is/links/wiki/statistics/correlation-analysis-chi-square.md/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Association Rules</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/pattern-mining/association-rules/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/pattern-mining/association-rules/</guid><description>Association rule is a method for pattern mining. In this article, we perform an association rule analysis of some demo data.
The Problem Defined Suppose we own a store called KIOSK. Here at KIOSK, we sell 4 different things.
Milk Croissant Coffee Fries We need to know what items are associated with each other when the customers are buying.
We have collected the following data. Beware that this small amount of data might not be enough for a real-world problem.
INDEX Items 1 croissant, milk 2 coffee, croissant 3 coffee, croissant 4 coffee, croissant, milk 5 coffee, milk 6 fries, milk 7 coffee, croissant, fries 8 croissant, fries 9 croissant, milk 10 croissant, fries, milk 11 coffee, croissant, milk The Rule, Support, and Confidence The Association rule has three components: the rule, the support, and the confidence.</description></item><item><title>Correlation Coefficient and Covariance for Numeric Data</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/statistics/correlation-coefficient/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/statistics/correlation-coefficient/</guid><description>Covariances Correlation coefficient is also known as the Pearson&amp;rsquo;s product moment coefficient. Review of Standard Deviation For a series of data A, we have the standard deviations
$$ \sigma_A = \sqrt{ \frac{ \sum (a_i - \bar A)^2 }{ n } }, $$
where $n$ is the number of elements in series A.
The standard deviation is very easy to understand. It is basically the average Eucleadian distance between the data points and the average value. In this article, we will take another point of view.
Now imagine we have two series $(a_i - \bar A)$ and $(a_j - \bar A)$. The geometric mean squared for $i=j$ is</description></item><item><title>Cramér's V</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/cards/statistics/cramers-v/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/cards/statistics/cramers-v/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>