<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Data Engineering on Datumorphism</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/categories/data-engineering/</link><description>Recent content in Data Engineering on Datumorphism</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://datumorphism.leima.is/categories/data-engineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Data Engineering for Data Scientists: Checklist</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/data-engeering-for-data-scientist/checklist/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/data-engeering-for-data-scientist/checklist/</guid><description>It is always good for a data scientist to understand more about data engineering, especially the blueprint of a fully productionized data platform.
There are several things to get into:
Connection to Data Sources Connect to DB Connect to Streaming Data Message Queues Connect to Website Scraping [[Node Crawler]] Node Crawler Write a crawler using nodejs API Other Data Services [[Data Storage]] Data Storage Storing big data Data Lake [[Data Warehouse]] Data Warehouse Take care of your data and your data will show you its power.</description></item><item><title>Data Storage</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/data-engeering-for-data-scientist/data-storage/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/data-engeering-for-data-scientist/data-storage/</guid><description> Many of the example are from the book by Adreas Kretz. Find the link to the book in the references section. Types of Storage and Data Here is a list 1
Files S3 Message Queues Kinesis Relational DB MySQL Postgres Non-relational DB Document Store MongoDB DocumentDB Key-Value Store HBase Redis Kretz2019 The Data Engineering Cookbook &amp;#160;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;</description></item><item><title>Data Processing</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/data-engeering-for-data-scientist/data-processing/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/data-engeering-for-data-scientist/data-processing/</guid><description>Many of the example are from the book by Adreas Kretz. Find the link to the book in the references section. Batch Process Kretz recommend to start from batch processing and move to streaming if needed 1.
Stream Process Three methods to stream data
At Least Once:  message gets processed once or multiple times never dropped e.g., time-based GPS data in fleet management, if the stream data has the same timestamp, then we just override the existing data, we do not care how many times the data is being processed or streamed. At Most Once: okay to drop a message only processed once at max e.</description></item><item><title>Scale Up</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/data-engeering-for-data-scientist/scale-up/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/data-engeering-for-data-scientist/scale-up/</guid><description>Many of the example are from the book by Adreas Kretz. Find the link to the book in the references section. Scaling Up Storage Scaling Up SQL DB SAN: Storage Area Network Use multiple servers on the DB storage to make the query faster.
Good for Read-only DB Not convinient to update DB Hadoop Hadoop:
Distributed storage Analysis 4 core modules:
Hadoop common background functionalities HDFS Divide into blocks Distribute MapReduce Old tech YARN Resource management The Hadoop Ecosystem:</description></item></channel></rss>