<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>wiki/model-selection/goodness-of-fit.md on Datumorphism</title><link>/links/wiki/model-selection/goodness-of-fit.md/</link><description>Recent content in wiki/model-selection/goodness-of-fit.md on Datumorphism</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="/links/wiki/model-selection/goodness-of-fit.md/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Akaike Information Criterion</title><link>/cards/statistics/aic/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/cards/statistics/aic/</guid><description>Suppose we have a model that describes the data generation process behind a dataset. The distribution by the model is denoted as $\hat f$. The actual data generation process is described by a distribution $f$.
We ask the question:
How good is the approximation using $\hat f$?
To be more precise, how much information is lost if we use our model dist $\hat f$ to substitute the actual data generation distribution $f$?</description></item><item><title>Bayesian Information Criterion</title><link>/cards/statistics/bic/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/cards/statistics/bic/</guid><description>BIC is Bayesian information criterion, it replaced the $+2k$ term in AIC with $k\ln n$
$$ \mathrm{BIC} = -2\ln p(y|\hat\theta) + k\ln n = \ln \left(\frac{n^k}{p^2}\right) $$
$n$ is the observations. We prefer the model with a small BIC.</description></item><item><title>Model Comparison</title><link>/wiki/model-selection/model-selection/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/wiki/model-selection/model-selection/</guid><description>The parsimony model comes from the idea of Occam&amp;rsquo;s razor: We choose the simple model that has more explanatory power.
The instance theory is a good model to explain the lexical decision task but it is not the only one. However, it simply makes it popular.
What is a Good Model? A good model should be presumably
plausibility balance of parsimony and goodness-of-fit coherence of the underlying assumptions easy to understand when it breaks down consistency with known results especially with the simple and basic phenomena ability to explain rather than describe data extent to which model predictions can be falsified through experiments.</description></item><item><title>Parsimony of Models</title><link>/wiki/model-selection/parsimony-of-models/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/wiki/model-selection/parsimony-of-models/</guid><description>For models with a lot of parameters, the goodness-of-fit is very likely to be very high. However, it is also likely to generalize bad. So we need measure of generalizability
Here parsinomy gives us a few advantages.
easy to perceive better generalizations</description></item></channel></rss>