<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>growing on Datumorphism</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/garden/growing/</link><description>Recent content in growing on Datumorphism</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://datumorphism.leima.is/garden/growing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Some Basic Ideas of Algorithms</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/algorithms/algorithms-basics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/algorithms/algorithms-basics/</guid><description>This set of notes on algorithms is not meant to be comprehensive or complete. These notes are being used as a skeleton framework. There are many useful books to learn about algorithms from a utilitarian point of view. I have listed a few in the references section.
Numerical recipes1 is a very comprehensive book that I used during my PhD. It covers almost all the algorithms you need for scientific computing.
Grokking Algorithms2 is another good book to learn the basics of algorithms. It is barely entry level but is fun to read.
An Outline Data Structure mind the data structure Basics of MapReduce mapreduce numrec Press, W.</description></item><item><title>Principles of Colors</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/data-visualization/colors/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/data-visualization/colors/</guid><description>ColorTeller
I wrote a python package called colorteller to help us manage and benchmark colors. Basic Concepts of Colors Color Wheel and Color Sphere There are two dimensions in the color wheel:
Hue Saturation When we add another dimension, lightness, to the wheel, we have a color sphere (1, 2).
Many color systems have been invented. Color wheel and color sphere are two examples of them.</description></item><item><title>Conformal Prediction</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/statistical-estimation/conformal-prediction/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/statistical-estimation/conformal-prediction/</guid><description>Conformal prediction is a method to predict a consistent confidence interval in an on-line setting. The algorithms is following the [[Neyman-Pearson hypothesis testing]] Neyman-Pearson Theory The Neyman-Pearson hypothesis testing tests two hypothesis, hypothesis $H$, and an alternative hypothesis $H_A$. Neyman-Pearson Lemma The Neyman-Pearson Lemma is an very intuitive lemma to understand how to choose a hypothesis. The lecture notes from PennState is a very good read on this topic1. An example For simplicity, we assume that there exists a test statistic $T$ and $T$ can be used to measure how likely the hypothesis $H$ is true, e.g., the hypothesis $H$ is false, corresponds to $T$ … framework, thus providing solid theoretical support for the predicted region.</description></item><item><title>Diffusion Models for Forecasting</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/energy-based-model/diffusion-model/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/machine-learning/energy-based-model/diffusion-model/</guid><description>Objective In a denoising diffusion model, given
an input $\mathbf x^0$ drawn from a complicated and unknown distribution $q(\mathbf x^0)$, we find
a latent space with a simple and manageable distribution, e.g., normal distribution, and the transformations from $\mathbf x^0$ to $\mathbf x^n$, as well as the transformations from $\mathbf x^n$ to $\mathbf x^0$. An Example For example, with $N=5$, the forward process is
flowchart LR x0 --> x1 --> x2 --> x3 --> x4 --> x5 and the reverse process is
flowchart LR x5 --> x4 --> x3 --> x2 --> x1 --> x0 The joint distribution we are searching for is</description></item><item><title>VSCode Setup Tests when Module is in a Different Folder</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/til/misc/vscode/vscode-setup-python-tests-with-module-in-src-folder/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/til/misc/vscode/vscode-setup-python-tests-with-module-in-src-folder/</guid><description>Use .env file</description></item></channel></rss>