<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>growing on Datumorphism</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/garden/growing/</link><description>Recent content in growing on Datumorphism</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://datumorphism.leima.is/garden/growing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Some Basic Ideas of Algorithms</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/algorithms/algorithms-basics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/algorithms/algorithms-basics/</guid><description>This set of notes on algorithms is not meant to be comprehensive or complete. These notes are being used as a skeleton framework. There are many useful books to learn about algorithms from a utilitarian point of view. I have listed a few in the references section.
Numerical recipes1 is a very comprehensive book that I used during my PhD. It covers almost all the algorithms you need for scientific computing.
Grokking Algorithms2 is another good book to learn the basics of algorithms. It is barely entry level but is fun to read.
An Outline Data Structure mind the data structure Basics of MapReduce mapreduce numrec Press, W.</description></item><item><title>Principles of Colors</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/data-visualization/colors/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/data-visualization/colors/</guid><description>ColorTeller
I wrote a python package called colorteller to help us manage and benchmark colors. Basic Concepts of Colors Color Wheel and Color Sphere There are two dimensions in the color wheel:
Hue Saturation When we add another dimension, lightness, to the wheel, we have a color sphere (1, 2).
Many color systems have been invented. Color wheel and color sphere are two examples of them.</description></item><item><title>VSCode Setup Tests when Module is in a Different Folder</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/til/misc/vscode/vscode-setup-python-tests-with-module-in-src-folder/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/til/misc/vscode/vscode-setup-python-tests-with-module-in-src-folder/</guid><description>Use .env file</description></item></channel></rss>