<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C on Datumorphism</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/tags/c/</link><description>Recent content in C on Datumorphism</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://datumorphism.leima.is/tags/c/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The C++ Language</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/programming-languages/cpp/references/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/programming-languages/cpp/references/</guid><description>C++!
Books The C++ Programming Language Programming Principles and Practice Using C++ The C++ Primer Lectures C++ Beginners Tutorial 1 (For Absolute Beginners) C++ Programming Introduction to C++ Coursear Course: C++ For C Programmers, Part A Top C++ Courses and Tutorials On SoloLearn: C++ Tutorial Practice SoloLearn provides this code playground that we can use to test c++ codes. There is also repl.it
Libraries For solving differential equations:</description></item><item><title>C/C++</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/programming-languages/cpp/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/programming-languages/cpp/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The C++ Language: Basics</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/programming-languages/cpp/basics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/programming-languages/cpp/basics/</guid><description>Make it Work Apart from the traditional way of running C++ code, Jupyter notebook has a clingkernel that make it possibel to run C++ in a Jupyter notebook. Here is the post: Interactive C++ for HPC.
Concepts Namespace Operators: assignment operators (=,+=,-=,*=,/=,%=), increment/decrement operator (++x,x++,--x,x--), relational operators (&amp;gt;,&amp;lt;,&amp;gt;=,&amp;lt;=,==,!=), logicl operators (&amp;amp;&amp;amp;,||,!), left shift (&amp;lt;&amp;lt;), extration operator (&amp;gt;&amp;gt;, or right shift), understand the operator precedence Variables: variable name starts with underscore or latin letters, Pascal case (PascalCase), Camel case (pascalCase) if/else and Loops: if (condition is true ){ then something } Data Types: string (double quote), character (char, 1 byte ASCII character, using single quote), float (4 bytes, always signed), double (8 bytes, always signed), long double (8 or 16 bytes, always signed), singed or unsigned short or long int (signed long int, unsigned int) Pointers: ampersand (&amp;amp;) accesses the address, pointer is variable thus needs to be declared using asterisk (*), can be declared to be int or double or float or char (int \*pt; int\* pt; int * pt;) Functions: overload, recursion Class: identity, atrributes, method/behavior, access specifiers (private or public or protected, by default it is set to private), instantiation of object (creating object), constructor, destructor, encapsulation, scope resolution operator (TheClassYouNeed::somefunction()), selection operator (dot member selection .</description></item><item><title>The C++ Language: Numerical Methods</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/programming-languages/cpp/numerical/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/programming-languages/cpp/numerical/</guid><description>Modularize The code should be designed to separate physics or model from numerical methods. Speed vectors are convenient but slow. 1 Do not copy arrays if not necessary. The example would be for a function return. Most of the time, we can pass the pointer of an array to the function and update the array itself without copying anything and no return is needed at all. inline function.</description></item></channel></rss>