<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>cards/statistics/mdl.md on Datumorphism</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/links/cards/statistics/mdl.md/</link><description>Recent content in cards/statistics/mdl.md on Datumorphism</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://datumorphism.leima.is/links/cards/statistics/mdl.md/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Model Selection</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/model-selection/model-selection/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/model-selection/model-selection/</guid><description>Suppose we have a generating process that generates some numbers based on a distribution. Based on a data sample, we could reconstruct some sort of theoretical models to represent the actual generating process.
Which is a Good Model? (1)The black curve represent the generating process. The red rectangle is a very simple model that captures some major samples. The blue step-wise model is capturing more sample data but with more parameters.
In the above example, the red model on the left is not that good in most cases while the blue model seems to be better. In reality, the choice depends on the usage of the model.</description></item><item><title>MDL and Neural Networks</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/model-selection/mdl-and-neural-networks/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/wiki/model-selection/mdl-and-neural-networks/</guid><description>Minimum Description Length ( [[MDL]] Minimum Description Length MDL is a measure of how well a model compresses data by minimizing the combined cost of the description of the model and the misfit. ) can be used to construct a concise network. A fully connected network has great expressing power but it is easily overfitting.
One strategy is to apply constraints to the networks:
Limit the connections; Shared weights in subgroups of the network; Constrain the weights using some probability distributions. By minimizing the MDL of the network and the misfits on the data, we can build a concise network. Based on the [[Source Coding Theorem]] Coding Theory Concepts The code function produces code words.</description></item><item><title>Fisher Information Approximation</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/cards/statistics/fia/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/cards/statistics/fia/</guid><description>FIA is a method to describe the minimum description length ( [[MDL]] Minimum Description Length MDL is a measure of how well a model compresses data by minimizing the combined cost of the description of the model and the misfit. ) of models,
$$ \mathrm{FIA} = -\ln p(y | \hat\theta) + \frac{k}{2} \ln \frac{n}{2\pi} + \ln \int_\Theta \sqrt{ \operatorname{det}[I(\theta)] d\theta } $$
$I(\theta)$: Fisher information matrix of sample size 1. $$I_{i,j}(\theta) = E\left( \frac{\partial \ln p(y| \theta)}{\partial \theta_i}\frac{ \partial \ln p (y | \theta) }{ \partial \theta_j } \right)$$.</description></item><item><title>Kolmogorov Complexity</title><link>https://datumorphism.leima.is/cards/statistics/kolmogorov-complexity/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datumorphism.leima.is/cards/statistics/kolmogorov-complexity/</guid><description>Description of Data
The measurement of complexity is based on the observation that the compressibility of data doesn&amp;rsquo;t depend on the &amp;ldquo;language&amp;rdquo; used to describe the compression process that much. This makes it possible for us to find a universal language, such as a universal computer language, to quantify the compressibility of the data.
One intuitive idea is to use a programming language to describe the data. If we have a sequence of data,
0,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,13,14,15,16,17,18,19,20,&amp;hellip;,9999
It takes a lot of space if we show the complete sequence. However, our math intuition tells us that this is nothing but a list of consecutive numbers from 0 to 9999.</description></item></channel></rss>